Finding aid for the Jay Ruby Collection on Coffee House Positano, circa 1950-1960s LSC.2214
UCLA Library Special Collections
Jay Ruby Collection on Coffee House Positano
circa 1950-1960s
UCLA Library Special Collections
Jay Ruby
LSC.2214
4.2 linear feet (1 half box, 1 oversize flat box, 1 painting, 1 table)
Coffee House Positano was a Malibu café and performance space (1957-1963) operated by Mike Dutton and Lorees Yerby off the Pacific Coast Highway. The café was known as a center of Bohemian life in Southern California. Collection was assembled by Jay Ruby and contains photographs, original and photocopies/printed scans of Positano bulletins and announcements, correspondence of waitress Joan Laine, and various ephemera related to the Positano and Malibu bohemian community.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jay Ruby, 2012. Gift of Joan Laine, 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9980278183606533
Biography/History
Coffee House Positano was a Malibu café and performance space (1957-1963) operated by Mike Dutton and Lorees Yerby off the Pacific Coast Highway. The café was known as a center of Bohemian life in Southern California and was frequented by notable Los Angeles artists, writers, and entertainment industry types including Allen Ginsberg, Ray Bradbury, and Keith Finch. Jay Ruby was an undergraduate at UCLA and worked as a dishwasher at Positano while living on the property from 1957-1959, in addition to participating in the community. After the closing of the café, the property transformed into the Budwood artists colony until the 1993 Malibu fire consumed the property.
Ruby later became a professor Emeritus of Anthropology at Temple University, and has researched and wrote extensively on Positano. Joan Laine was a waitress at Coffee Shop Positano (1957-1959).
Source: https://www.malibutimes.com/malibu_life/article_3d0d3bdf-4267-50fb-a6c8-6d6fee3654e4.html
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials compiled by Jay Ruby documenting the history of Coffee House Positano and its related community of artists and patrons. Included are photographs, original and photocopies/printed scans of Positano bulletins and announcements, art and performance ephemera, correspondence, artworks, and furniture.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Coffeehouse Positano and Malibu Bohemia, Approx. 1950-1969
Series 2: Joan Laine materials, Approx. 1959-1963
Series 3: Artworks and Furniture, Approx. 1959-1963
The materials have retained their original folder organization from Jay Ruby.
Related Material
Lorees Yerby papers. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Artists -- California -- Los Angeles.; Coffeehouses -- California -- Malibu.; Malibu (Calif.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Counterculture -- California -- Malibu; Bohemianism -- California -- Malibu.; Coffee House Positano
- Series 1: Coffee House Positano and Malibu Bohemia, circa 1950s-1960s
  Scope and Content
  Contains photographs of Jay Ruby and others, original and photocopies/printed scans of Positano bulletins and announcements, copies of clippings/articles, script for Desire Trapped by the Trail, exhibit invitation for Ed Pagac and Ruth Levy at Keith Finch Studio, assorted printed digital maps.
  - Photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Four photographs: 3 Jay Ruby, 1 group shot Jay Ruby and others.
  - Positano and Malibu Ephemera, 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Desire Trapped Script, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Also contains photograph with Colleen Guadelouple, Jay Ruby, Bill Otto, and others unidentified.
  - Playhouse, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Old Maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Positano Bulletins, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Materials are photocopies and printed scan copies.
  - Miscellaneous Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cafe Espresso Kick Article, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Initial Announcement, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Raitt Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Property Maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Joan Laine materials, circa 1959-1963
  Contains a selection of letters to Joan Laine, a waitress at Coffee House Positano, 1957-1959, including letters from Ed Pagac, an artist who was active at Positano from its beginning to its end, Pasitano co-owner Lorees Yerby, and Positano waitress Shirley Jonas.
  - Correspondence, circa 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Artworks and Furniture, Approx 1950s-1960s
  Series contains artworks and furniture associated with Coffee House Positano.
  - Oil painting by Edward Pagac, undated; Unframed, Approx. 40"x30", by Edward Pagac, a painter who frequented Positano. (Box 2)
  - Concrete Crucifix, undated; Approx. 17"x15" (Box 3)
  - Chess Table, undated; Wooden table, Approx. 41"x24"x28" (Box 4)